<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new inuention of shooting fire-shafts in long-bowes VVherein, besides the maner of making them, there is contained a briefe discourse of the vsefulnesse of them in our moderne warres, by sea and land. Published by a true patriot for the common good of his native countrey of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854513</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 991:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new inuention of shooting fire-shafts in long-bowes VVherein, besides the maner of making them, there is contained a briefe discourse of the vsefulnesse of them in our moderne warres, by sea and land. Published by a true patriot for the common good of his native countrey of England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Iohn Bartlet, at the gilt Cup in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. M.D.c.xxviii. [1628]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The imprint date is made with turned C's.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at head, affecting title and some page numbers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bow and arrow --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW INVENTION OF Shooting FIRE-SHAFTS in <hi>Long-Bowes:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein, beſides the maner of making them, there is contained a briefe Diſcourſe of the vſefulneſſe of them in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Warres, by Sea and Land.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by a true Patriot for the common good of his native Countrey of England.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>DEVS PROVIDEBIT</head>
               <p>IVSTVS VIVET FIDE</p>
               <p>R Y</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlet,</hi> the gilt Cup in Cheape-ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> M.D.C. XXVIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19939:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19939:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19939:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19939:3"/>
            <head>The Vſe of FIRE-SHAFTS: together with the manner how to make, and <hi>ſhoote them out of Long-Bowes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He coſt, incumbrance, and ſmall auayle of Corſlets for Field or Fortreſſe in our moderne Warres, may be ſufficiently knowne to all experienced men in the profeſſion of Armes; yet dare I not auow, that Bowes and fiery Arrowes would be more ſeruiceable in all occaſions, becauſe the preualent cuſtome of receiued traditions, is much more plauſible than reaſon. Onely I will lay downe ſome probable (though but imaginary) ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the one, and ſome ſeeming (if not experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented) defects of the other; till time adde forme and farther credit to the Eſſay.</p>
            <p>My Ouerture is no myſterious ſubtile Artifice, all that can recommend it, is the employment: but if any man be pleaſed to proue the demonſtration, I doubt not of his patience in reading this diſcourſe. Where firſt I would aduiſe by way of Preface (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by ſome experience I haue learned, how
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19939:4"/>hardly men are drawne to fence themſelues againſt they ſee not what) that no train'd Souldier arme himſelfe by any Argument of mine againſt the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like inſtitution of prouiſionary Corſlets. For thoſe who haue ill neighbours (which no ſo bleſt eſtate as ours can euer bee without) muſt ſuite themſelues (if better may not be) with Armes of like defence; leſt enemies inuited by their nakedneſſe, attempt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of their liberties, together with the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their bloud.</p>
            <p>I know not the iuſt price of a ſeruiceable Corſlet at this time; but ſure I thinke it farre exceedes the charge of all that furniture an Archer ſtands in need off. Beſides the daily perquiſites when ere they are employed, of oyling, buckles, thongs; ſmall things, but very neceſſary, and which ſometimes can ſcarce be had for money. Their weight (I confeſſe) is little to an able man, and the faſhion not much vneaſie for him that hath them ſhaped to his own proportion: but when ſlender fare, and hard lodging abate mens ſtrength, and that the ſhape of body muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained within the Corſlet (as commonly men ſee in ſeruice;) and amongſt train'd Souldiers (where the Maſter to his ſeruant, or the Father to his ſonne deliuer Armes as they haue made them for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or for ſome other of more vnequall ſtature) then not to ſpeak of the ridiculous ſhew they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make, the incumbrance is ſo great that hardly any patience can indure it long. They foule &amp; fret mens cloathes, &amp; adde extremities to the exceſſe of cold and heate: ſo that in Winter men are loath to put them on, and in Summer they throw them off in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19939:4"/>ſpite of all command. The helpe is, on a march to put them into Carts, where either much time muſt bee ſpent (too precious) to pack them vp in order; or they muſt (as commonly they are) be thrown together on heapes, that when they are taken off again vpon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they are ſo bruiſed, broken, and confuſedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynted, that men which put them on ſeeme rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained in irons, than harneſſed with an armor of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And though this inconuenience be leſſe ſenſible in Holland (where ſea and interſection of many waters yeelds conuenient tranſportation by boate, almoſt to euery town) yet the proofe they haue had euen there, may ſerue to iuſtifie the truth of what men finde in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts.</p>
            <p>If Armours were all musket-proofe, and men well able to endure them, their vſe were excellent for many purpoſes: but ſuch men ſcarſly find we amongſt many to guard a pettardier, or make diſcouery on a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp; works of quick diſpatch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>par'd with marches, breaches, or field-skirmiſhes. But light armours (as we now haue them) though compleate with head-peece, taſſets, gauntlets, will be of no defence againſt an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that mingles bullets with his Arrowes: for I ſeek not to perſwade the vſe of Bowes in ſteed of Guns, but that by due accouplement of both, more hands might in leſſe roome bee brought to fight at once; a part of chiefeſt excellence in marſhalling of men.</p>
            <p>Some men I know haue Armours in ſo great eſteem, that they thinke for a Souldier to quit his ſword, is (in extremities) a fault more pardonable, than to caſt away his Corſlet: their reaſon is, that though it be bad to loſe his weapon of aſſault, yet much more deſperately ill to abandon all the meanes of ſelfe-defence. And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19939:5"/>they alleage that in former times, one Souldier was puniſhed for caſting away his Target though hee kept his Sword: and another was rewarded, for that in like extremitie he left his Sword &amp; kept his Target. But if Corſlets hold no proportion with the weapons of our modern wars; if Muskets, Carrabines, Piſtols, all predomine, then are they now no inſtruments of ſelfe-defence, but meere impediments. And if any wil obiect the aduantage of Pike-men armd againſt a ſtand of vnarmd Pikes, I referre me to the teſtimony of old Souldiers, how often in their life time they haue ſeen a firme (I ſay a firme) encounter in the field, twixt Piles and Pikes. And yet if ſo it happen, I know not whether the bodies free agilitie on the one ſide, or the temper of an armour on the other, would yeeld a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes of preſeruation. But ſure I thinke it is our chiefeſt diſaduantage, that they ſo ſeldom enterſhock; for the thigh-bone, ſhin-bone, &amp; the armes of Engliſh, longer than of French, and much leſſe foggy than of Duch, to take large ſtrides, and retch and winde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into all poſtures, makes much for vs at puſh of Pike; as doth like feature of our Limbes (more apt than of our neighbours) to practiſe ſhooting in the Long-bow. Therefore what I ſpeake in generall of Corſlets extends not wholly vnto Pikes: for ſome of them may bee of vſe in open field to ſupply the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of Arrowes, as bowes might ſerue to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard the ſlow diſpatch of Muskettiers, in trauerſing to ſhoote and charge againe.</p>
            <p>There was a time when Launces were eſteemed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable, as Corſlets at this day: but by diſcourſe &amp; farther triall, men haue found that they are bootleſſe in our Wars; &amp; time with better diſcourſe may worke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19939:5"/>the ſame effect in that I treate off. Meane while the practice of the bow may be receiued, though we retain the vſe of the Corſlet; for if the one bee ſmall incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance on the body, the other will be little burthen at the backe, and if to reſt the left hand on the pike, ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men to draw a ſtronger bowe, that ingenious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of ſcruing both together will be beſt; otherwiſe to lay the pikes (in time of ſeruice) not longſt the fyles (as vſually men doe) but thwart the rankes, will be no let at all to the Archier, but help to keep him in an euen front, and ſo they will lye ready to take vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine when time ſhalbe.</p>
            <p>Now if the fire-ſhafrs which are propoſed, bee of that efficacy which I pretend, no fairer engine was there euer vſed in warre; the coſt not great, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrance none at all: they are neate, portable, and ſo mannageable, that euen children may make their ſport with them, and youths of any growth may doe good ſeruice, making their practice onely with the common arrowes; than which, there can bee no more noble recreation. But if at feſtiuall times, a Bull (in ſtead of bayting him with dogges) were tyed at ſtake, or ſheweld in with Archiers, conueniently placed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Common, or other ſpacious place; men might then make triall with their fire-ſhafts (a braue and manlike ſport) where happely the madding of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged beaſt (beſides inuring men to conflict) would teach ſome profitable ſtratagem for warre.</p>
            <p>Whateuer martiall feates by land are left recorded of our nation in old times, haue been moſt commonly atchieued by vertue of the Bowe; which vertue may be artificially renewed, if a grounded apprehenſion that bullets are more mortall, take not from vs all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19939:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>that arrowes may not onely bee deliuered more ſpeedily, more ſafely, and in greater numbers at once; but alſo will flee farther (ſhot at randon) than bullets reach point-blanke. Aduantages, which well obſerued, will fruſtrate all the efficacy, by depriuing men of the vſe of whatſomeuer other weapon: for Bow-men placed behind a Paraper, a ſtand of Pikes, or mannuple of Muſquettiers, may ſhowre down ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant drops of fire, like Sodoms raine, vpon an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, as will not onely annoy the Pikes, and rout the Horſe, but altogether diſable the Muſquettier; as may be gathered by the ſuppoſitions which compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely I ſhall lay downe in that which followes: inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting only vpon the regular imbattelling of men, and leauing to diſcretion the difference of accidentall formes, according to the variety of occurrents.</p>
            <p>The form of a regular Squadron, whoſe body con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of Corſlets, leaues a great ſpace of ground before it voide; and as much more ſupplied with idle hands, and thoſe idle hands expoſed to ineuitable hazzard. The whole ſpace before the Corſlets, is, and muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be left voide; leſt the Muſquettiers wearied, wanting munition, or otherwiſe ouercharged by any ſudden incurſion of Horſe, ſhould haſtily make retrait vpon the front of their owne Corſlets, and ſo depriue themſelues of their owne defence: for in that caſe the Corſlets are no refuge.</p>
            <p>This ſpace before the Corſlets being then ſo left voide, &amp; the mannuples of Muſquettiers being drawn forth to skirmiſh on the flanques, in any imaginable manner; the Corſlets are but ſo many idle handes, yet ſtand expoſed to great mortality during the skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh of the Muſquettiers: for Corſlets are no muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet-proofe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19939:6"/>nor dare the Muſquettiers draw forth ſo far before, as to leaue them out of reach of the enemies muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, leſt by ſome ſudden fury of Horſe, themſelues ſhould be ouer-run ere they could make an orderly retrait. But ſuppoſe they make an orderly retrait (for continuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and agitation, with often bruiſing of the Muſquet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their bodies (if nothing elſe) will force them at the length to make retrait) the ſuccour they ſhall finde on the flanques, or in the reare of the Corſlets, will aſſuredly be very ſmall; for the enemies Horſe aduancing forward, and diſcharging vpon a Carico, will in ſhort time ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten the Corſlets, wounding and maiming in the face, and armes, and other bared parts (if not through the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Corſlet) the formoſt &amp; braueſt of them, that the reſt men may beleeue wil eaſily giue ground, and open ranks to an vtter ouerthrow. Or admit at the beſt, that our Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetties ſo diſcomfit the enemies that we put them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait, I ſay not, that our Corſlets will then ſerue vs for no vſe; but a prudent Commander, I thinke, will either hold his aduantage with Muſquettiers, or purſue it to an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with his Horſe; and then no weapon to the ſingle ſword, though piſtols, pikes, and euen muſquet ſtockes, are ſometimes inſtruments of execution.</p>
            <p>For a fortreſſe, the chiefeſt vſe of Corſlets that I know, is at an aſſault after battery, where (as well within as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out) they haue beene vſually employed amongſt other weapons. Whether they or other weapons be in that caſe more ſeruiceable, I need not to contend; it is ſufficient that aſſault and battery is almoſt euery where layed aſide. They without make their approches vnderground to the ditch, and throw the ditch if it be dry; and if it haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they paſſe a gallery to the wall of the fortreſſe, and there myne and blow vp, gaining their ground by hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breadths,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19939:7"/>and employ their Ordnance only againſt the flanquers, and to cleare the Curtens; for experience hath taught that this way (though more ſlow) makes an aſſured paſſage with leſſe coſt and loſſe of men; chiefly of thoſe moſt able bodies and valiant ſpirits, which at an aſſault were commonly employed on both ſides. And this which hath been ſaid of Corſlets without, may ſhew their ſmall auaile within a fortreſſe; where the ordinary defence is countermine, retrenchment, fire-workes and guns. As for Corſlets in a ſally, if the Muſquettiers paſſe not the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par &amp; Reualins, the vſe is very little; and if they paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond, it is no more than hath beene ſaid before in field-ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the deficiences that ſome years ſince took vp my imagination, and made me conſider, whether by the ſubuention of ſome other more proportionable engine, the ſubalterne and ſlow diſcharging of the Muſquet, might not bee ſecur'd againſt the ſudden fury and ſwift incurſion of the Horſe; as alſo whether the voide ground and vacant time might not be more ſeruiceably ſupplyed with fighting hands: and my opinion was, that if the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row could be ſo enforced with fire-workes, as might giue no impediment to the flight &amp; quick deliuery, the thing were found. But hauing my ſelf no skill in fire-works (had not mine owne ouer-aboundant leiſure inuited mee ſince that, to tamper ſomewhat in ſuch kinde of engenry) I had layed aſide my conceipt of long-bowes, which I now communicate; beginning as before, with the examination of their benefit for the body of a ſquadron in field-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: where it is euident that the Muſquetters may be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced before the front with a mutuall defence; for as the Muſquettiers are defended by the arrowes from ouer their heads againſt the enemies horſe, ſo the Archiers are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19939:7"/>defended by the bodies of the Muſquettiers (who are in no more danger, but yeeld more ſhelter than before) againſt the enemies bullets; and, which is the chiefeſt aduantage in fight, all hands ſhalbe employed at once: for at the ſame time with the Muſquettiers, the Archers may ſhoot ouer ſuch vollies of fiery arrowes, as ſhall (though leſſe mortall) giue an enemy no leſſe occaſion to looke about him than the bullers. Or becauſe a totall innouation of armes and order may ſeem too hazzar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous, where the liues of men and honor of the field are layed at ſtake; if the fire-ſhafts, I ſpeak of, flee but twelueſcore yards (and I know by ſome good proofe, that they will flee more than fourteen, from any practis'd arme of common ſtrength) the Archiers may be placed behind foure ranks of Corſlets (as many as at once can charge their Pikes to purpoſe) and from thence without impediment to any of their own (either Pikes or Muſquettiers) performe as much as hath been ſaid before. And if the ſtore an Archier beares about him, will not ſuffice to maintaine the fight throughout, one horſe for euery hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred bowmen, will beare munition as much as will ſerue the turne; and when all failes, they haue their Pike &amp; Head-piece to defend themſelues; for theſe a man may march withall, beſides his bowe and arrowes very eaſily.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe I am fallen into diſcourſe of arranging men in ſquadron, I may without detracting from any authoriſed diſcipline, or from the more approued cuſtomes of our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duated martialiſts (for I will propound it but in caſe that long bowes be receiued in ſtead of Corſlets) ſhew how in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the Muſquettiers may moſt commodiouſly ſhift ſtation in a skirmiſh; and open place for ranks that follow, &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for the whole body (Bows aſwell as Muſquettiers) to giue or gaine ground on an enemy, inſenſibly. And that I may be the better vnderſtood, I will expreſſe my ſelfe by a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mannuple of thirty Muſquettiers, fiue in file and fixe in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19939:8"/>front; the formoſt ranke whereof hauing diſcharged, ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſelfe by three in file on either flanque, ſo leauing ſpace voide for the next ſucceeding ranke to aduance in euen front with the former of thoſe files; where they likewiſe hauing diſcharged their muſquets, ſhall file themſelues on either flanque as did the firſt, leauing like open way for them that follow to draw forward. By which order of ſucceſſion, the firſt ranke will haue leaſure to charge again &amp; reſume his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place, without retiring to the reare of all, as uſually they do, and as indeed is requiſite when they will giue ground: for then the firſt ranke hauing diſcharged, may turne away (three on each flanque) vnto the reare, &amp; there rally themſelues: the reſt, each after other doing the like, and taking place behind, till the whole ground wheron they firſt began to skirmiſh be left voide, and the way left free againe for the formoſt ranke, without aduancing to diſcharge anew. This I think ſufficient to explaine my meaning; I will therefore now proceed to ſhew the benefit of fire-ſhafts for a fortreſſe. where they ſeem to mee incomparably vſefull as well within as without: for they may be ſhot from behind a breſt of defence, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering any part of our body to the enemy. No enemy can ſo ſhelter himſelfe in his approches, but that theſe fire-ſhafts may fall vpon him. They will put to great trouble and haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the Cannoniers that plye the Artillery on batteries, where bullets cannot hit them. They will ſerue to ſet on fire the enemies tents and cabening. And the blaze of them in the night will in all likelihood make ſuch diſcouery, that Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quettiers ſtanding ready to leuell where they fall, may aime at the enemy as by day, &amp; keep perdues, engeniers, workmen, and thoſe that watch by night in ſuch continuall awe, as will greatly hinder, if not wholly driue them from their watch and labour. Yea with reaſon it may be thought they will facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate all attempts by night; for the eie of enemie will be ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19939:8"/>dazelled, and his body ſo clearely diſcerned by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of them, that men may boldly aſſaile an enemy by night, and ſafely make retrait in all occaſions.</p>
            <p>Manie other, and indeed indeterminable are the vſes that by coniecture may be drawne from ſuch like arrowes ſhot out of the long-bowe, both by ſea and land; in particular to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue an enemy of the vſe of his ſailes at a great diſtance; for the canuas will take fire like tinder, and vaniſh by enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the winde in ſudden flame, if any arrow faſten in it, as among many ſome aſſuredly will do. I may therefore ſay, that as other parts of that munition which hath been patternd out from heauen in former times, haue in this latter age beene neerly reſembled by ordinarie meanes on earth with great effect; as thundring haileſtones by ſhooting bullets, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whole townes brimſtone, ſalt, and burning like the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of the foure cities, by mynes of powder, conſiſting of brimſtone, ſalt-peeter, and burnt coale; ſo this newer imitation of ſharpe arrowes with coales of Iuniper, and of mingling haileſtones with coales of fire (both which wee reade of) may be found in the practice (for eaſe and variety of vſe) to be of great importance: and in that opinion I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to the welfare of my Country, whoſe peculiar wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon of aduantage it will be; at leaſt for to ſupply our want of Horſe, which we neither can tranſport to forraine employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in conuenient numbers, nor are by nature ſo enclin'd to tend with art and induſtry, as other of our neighbours doe.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Sapienter idem.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19939:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>How to make and ſhoote Fire-ſhafts out of the Long-bowe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et the Fire-ſhafts haue one end feathered and ſhaped, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of an ordinary arrow, and the other end fitted with a pipe of latten, ten inched long or more, at diſcretion, a bearded head of iron faſt glued into it, with a ſocket of wood, &amp; a touch-hole made cloſe by it, with ſome little reuerſe to ſtop the arrow from piercing ſo deepe into a mans cloaths, the flanques of a horſe, or other marke of eaſie paſſage, as to choake the fire. The ſhaft may be made faſt within the pipe (if men ſo pleaſe) with hard waxe; which melting as the pipe groweth hote, will make it very difficult to draw the arrow from where it lights.</p>
            <p>Arrowes to make a blaze by night, as alſo thoſe that are to ſhoote into the ſailes of a ſhip or an enemies tent, muſt haue the touch-hole within an inch of the ſhaft, and the reuerſe a little aboue the touch-hole, to ſtay the arrow while the marke takes fire.</p>
            <p>The pipe muſt be filled with this mixture bruiſed very ſmal &amp; hard ram'd in; Gunpowder &amp; ſalt-peeter a like proportion, &amp; brimſtone halfe ſo much, with ſome ſmall quantity of camphir (if men pleaſe) to make it operate more ſtrongly where the mark is wet. If the mixture burne too quicke, adde brimſtone; if too ſlowe, adde powder.</p>
            <p>To ſtop the touch-hole that the mixture runne not forth, &amp; to take fire when you meane to ſhoote, ſeeth cotten-candlewicke in vineger and gunpowder bruiſed very ſmall; and when it is throughly ſoaked and well dryed, take a ſmall quantity (rolled a little in the former mixture) and ſtop the touch-hole therewith.</p>
            <p>The Fire-ſhaft being made, and filled in this manner, take the Bowe with a match well lighted into your left hand, after the manner of Muſquettiers; then hold the Arrow ready nocked in the Bowe, after the manner of Archers. Laſtly, give fire, returne your match, and deliuer the Arrow.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19939:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
